<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Alternative Wild Magic Sorcerer</name>
		<description>Wild Magic Sorcerer from Marco's Homebrew</description>
		<update version="0.2.8">
			<file name="Alt_WMS.xml" url="https://github.com/marco-om97/DnDHomebrew/blob/main/Alt_WMS.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
	<element name="Unstable Spell" type="Class Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_CLASS_FEATURE_SORCERER_METAMAGIC_UNSTABLE_SPELL">
		<supports>Metamagic</supports>
		<description>
			<p>When you cast a spell that forces a target to make a saving throw, you can spend 2 sorcery points (1 if you are a Wild Magic Sorcerer) to have the first saving throw against one target of the spell change its save ability determined by random chance. Roll a d6, and the target's first saving throw is changed. If you roll the ability that matches the spell's default saving throw, you may choose which ability to target for this spell's first saving throw on one target.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>
			<p>When you cast a spell that forces a target to make a saving throw, you can spend 2 sorcery points (1 if you are a Wild Magic Sorcerer) to have the first saving throw against one target of the spell change its save ability determined by random chance. Roll a d6, and the target's first saving throw is changed to target the ability corresponding to the table below. If you roll the ability that matches the spell's default saving throw, you may choose which ability to target for this spell's first saving throw on one target.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">UNSTABLE SPELL</h5>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td>Roll</td><td>Saving Throw</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td>1</td><td>Strength</td></tr>
				<tr><td>2</td><td>Dexerity</td></tr>
				<tr><td>3</td><td>Constitution</td></tr>
				<tr><td>4</td><td>Intelligence</td></tr>
				<tr><td>5</td><td>Wisdom</td></tr>
				<tr><td>6</td><td>Charisma</td></tr>
			</table>
			</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Alternative Wild Magic" type="Archetype" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_WILD_MAGIC">
		<supports>Sorcerous Origin</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your innate magic comes from the wild forces of chaos that underlie the order of creation. You might have endured exposure to some form of raw magic, perhaps through a planar portal leading to Limbo, the Elemental Planes, or the mysterious Far Realm. Perhaps you were blessed by a powerful fey creature or marked by a demon. Or your magic could be a fluke of your birth, with no apparent cause or reason. However it came to be, this chaotic magic churns within you, waiting for any outlet.</p>
			<p>Your choice grants you features when you choose it at 1st level and again at 6th, 14th, and 18th level.</p>
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_MAGIC_SURGE" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_INNATE_INSTABILITY" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_TIDES_OF_CHAOS" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BEND_LUCK" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_SORCERY" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CONTROLLED_CHAOS" />
			<div element="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPELL_BOMBARDMENT" />
			<h5 class="caption">WILD MAGIC SURGE</h5>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td>d100</td><td>Effect</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td>01-02</td><td>Roll on this table at the start of each of your turns for the next minute, ignoring this result on subsequent rolls.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>03-04</td><td>For the next minute, you can see any invisible creature if you have line of sight to it.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>05-06</td><td>A modron chosen and controlled by the DM appears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of you, then disappears I minute later.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>07-08</td><td>You cast Fireball as a 3rd-level spell centered on yourself.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>09-10</td><td>You cast Magic Missile as a 5th-level spell.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>11-12</td><td>Roll a d10. Your height changes by a number of inches equal to the roll. If the roll is odd, you shrink. If the roll is even, you grow.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>13-14</td><td>You cast Confusion centered on yourself.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>15-16</td><td>For the next minute, you regain 5 hit points at the start of each of your turns.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>17-18</td><td>You grow a long beard made of feathers that remains until you sneeze, at which point the feathers explode out from your face.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>19-20</td><td>You cast Grease centered on yourself.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>21-22</td><td>Creatures have disadvantage on saving throws against the next spell you cast in the next minute that involves a saving throw.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>23-24</td><td>Your skin turns a vibrant shade of blue. A Remove Curse spell can end this effect.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>25-26</td><td>An eye appears on your forehead for the next minute. During that time, you have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>27-28</td><td>For the next minute, all your spells with a casting time of 1 action have a casting time of 1 bonus action.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>29-30</td><td>You teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>31-32</td><td>You are transported to the Astral Plane until the end of your next turn, after which time you return to the space you previously occupied or the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>33-34</td><td>Maximize the damage of the next damaging spell you cast within the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>35-36</td><td>Roll a d10. Your age changes by a number of years equal to the roll. If the roll is odd, you get younger (minimum 1 year old). If the roll is even, you get older.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>37-38</td><td>1d6 flumphs controlled by the DM appear in unoccupied spaces within 60 feet of you and are frightened of you. They vanish after 1 minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>39-40</td><td>You regain 2d10 hit points.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>41-42</td><td>You turn into a potted plant until the start of your next turn. While a plant, you are incapacitated and have vulnerability to all damage. If you drop to 0 hit points, your pot breaks, and your form reverts.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>43-44</td><td>For the next minute, you can teleport up to 20 feet as a bonus action on each of your turns.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>45-46</td><td>You cast Levitate on yourself.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>47-48</td><td>A unicorn controlled by the DM appears in a space within 5 feet of you, then disappears 1 minute later.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>49-50</td><td>You can't speak for the next minute. Whenever you try, pink bubbles float out of your mouth.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>51-52</td><td>A spectral shield hovers near you for the next minute, granting you a +2 bonus to AC and immunity to Magic Missile.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>53-54</td><td>You are immune to being intoxicated by alcohol for the next 5d6 days.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>55-56</td><td>Your hair falls out but grows back within 24 hours.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>57-58</td><td>For the next minute, any flammable object you touch that isn't being worn or carried by another creature bursts into flame.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>59-60</td><td>You regain your lowest-level expended spell slot.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>61-62</td><td>For the next minute, you must shout when you speak.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>63-64</td><td>You cast Fog Cloud centered on yourself.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>65-66</td><td>Up to three creatures you choose within 30 feet of you take 4d10 lightning damage.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>67-68</td><td>You are frightened by the nearest creature until the end of your next turn.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>69-70</td><td>Each creature within 30 feet of you becomes invisible for the next minute. The invisibility ends on a creature when it attacks or casts a spell.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>71-72</td><td>You gain resistance to all damage for the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>73-74</td><td>A random creature within 60 feet of you becomes poisoned for 1d4 hours.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>75-76</td><td>You glow with bright light in a 30-foot radius for the next minute. Any creature that ends its turn within 5 feet of you is blinded until the end of its next turn.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>77-78</td><td>You cast Polymorph on yourself. If you fail the saving throw, you turn into a sheep for the spell's duration.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>79-80</td><td>Illusory butterflies and flower petals flutter in the air within 10 feet of you for the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>81-82</td><td>You can take one additional action immediately.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>83-84</td><td>Each creature within 30 feet of you takes 1d10 necrotic damage. You regain hit points equal to the sum of the necrotic damage dealt.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>85-86</td><td>You cast Mirror Image.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>87-88</td><td>You cast Fly on a random creature within 60 feet of you.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>89-90</td><td>You become invisible for the next minute. During that time, other creatures can't hear you. The invisibility ends if you attack or cast a spell.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>91-92</td><td>If you die within the next minute, you immediately come back to life as if by the Reincarnate spell.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>93-94</td><td>Your size increases by one size category for the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>95-96</td><td>You and all creatures within 30 feet of you gain vulnerability to piercing damage for the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>97-98</td><td>You are surrounded by faint, ethereal music for the next minute.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>99-100</td><td>You regain all expended sorcery points.</td></tr>
			</table>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>Your innate magic comes from the wild forces of chaos that underlie the order of creation.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_MAGIC_SURGE" level="1" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_TIDES_OF_CHAOS" level="1" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_INNATE_INSTABILITY" level="1" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BEND_LUCK" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_SORCERY" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CONTROLLED_CHAOS" level="14" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPELL_BOMBARDMENT" level="18" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Innate Instability" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_INNATE_INSTABILITY_SURGE">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>1st-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>	
			<p>You learn Thaumaturgy, which doesn't count against the number of sorcerer cantrips you know. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Wild Magic Spells table. These spells don't count against the number of sorcerer spells you know.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you gain a level in this class, you can replace one spell from this feature with an evocation or transmutation spell from the sorcerer, bard, or wizard spell list of the same level.</p>
			<h5 class="caption">Wild Magic Spells</h5>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td>Sorcerer Level</td><td>Spells</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td>1st</td><td><em>chaos bolt, faerie fire</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>3rd</td><td><em>Nathair's mischief, misty step</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>5th</td><td><em>blink, hypnotic pattern</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>7th</td><td><em>confusion, polymorph</em></td></tr>
				<tr><td>9th</td><td><em>creation, Bigby's hand</em></td></tr>
			</table>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When you gain a level in this class, you can replace one spell from this feature with an evocation or transmutation spell from the sorcerer, bard, or wizard spell list of the same level.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Spell" name="Cantrip (Wild Magic)" supports="0,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)" level="1" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_THAUMATURGY" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="1st Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="1,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Chaos Bolt" level="1" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_CHAOS_BOLT" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="2nd Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="1,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Faerie Fire" level="1" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_FAERIE_FIRE" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="3rd Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="2,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Nathair's Mischief" level="3" default="ID_WOTC_FTOD_SPELL_NATHAIRS_MISCHIEF" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="4th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="2,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)" level="3" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_MISTY_STEP" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="5th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="3,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Blink" level="5" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_BLINK" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="6th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="3,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Hypnotic Pattern" level="5" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_HYPNOTIC_PATTERN" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="7th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="4,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Confusion" level="7" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONFUSION" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="8th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="4,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Polymorph" level="7" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_POLYMORPH" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="9th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="5,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)" level="9" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_CREATION" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
			<select type="Spell" name="10th Additional Spell (Wild Magic Spells)" supports="5,(Evocation||Transmutation),(Sorcerer||Bard||Wizard)||Bigby's Hand" level="9" default="ID_PHB_SPELL_BIGBYS_HAND" spellcasting="Sorcerer" allowReplace="false" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Wild Magic Surge" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_MAGIC_SURGE">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>1st-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>Starting when you choose this origin at 1st level, your spellcasting can unleash surges of untamed magic. After you cast a sorcerer spell of 1st-level or higher, roll a d10. If you roll a 1, immediately roll a d100 for the Wild Magic Surge table to create a magical effect. If that effect is a spell, it is too wild to be affected by your metamagic, and if it normally requires concentration, it doesn't require concentration in this case; the spell lasts for its full duration.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>After you cast a sorcerer spell of 1st-level or higher, roll a d10. If you roll a 1, immediately roll a d100 for the Wild Magic Surge table to create a magical effect. If that effect is a spell, it is too wild to be affected by your metamagic, and if it normally requires concentration, it doesn't require concentration in this case; the spell lasts for its full duration.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Tides of Chaos" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_TIDES_OF_CHAOS">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>1st-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>Starting at 1st level, you can manipulate the forces of chance and chaos to gain advantage on one attack roll, ability check, or saving throw. You can also consume Tides of Chaos to suppress a single Wild Magic Surge. After you do so, you must finish a long rest before you can use this feature again.</p>
			<p class="indent">While Tides of Chaos is expended, the chances for a wild magic surge increase. A surge happens when you now roll a 1 or 10 on the dice. After expended, you may regain the use Tides of Chaos at the end of your next Wild Magic Surge.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You can gain advantage on one attack roll, ability check, or saving throw.
			While Tides of Chaos is expended, the chances for a wild magic surge increase. A surge happens when you now roll a 1 or 10 on the dice. After expended, you may regain the use Tides of Chaos at the end of your next Wild Magic Surge.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Bend Luck" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_BEND_LUCK">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>6th-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>Starting at 6th level, you have the ability to twist fate using your wild magic. When another creature you can see makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction and spend 2 sorcery points to roll 1d4 and apply the number rolled as a bonus or penalty (your choice) to the creature’s roll. You can do so after the creature rolls but before any effects of the roll occur.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description>When another creature you can see makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can spend 2 sorcery points to roll 1d4 and apply the number rolled as a bonus or penalty to the creature’s roll. You can do so after the creature rolls but before any effects of the roll occur.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Wild Sorcery" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_WILD_SORCERY">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>6th-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>For the next metamagic you apply on a spell after using Bend Luck or after a Wild Magic surge, its sorcery point cost is reduced by 1 (minimum 0). You can only reduce the sorcery point cost this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus per long rest. In addition, at 6th level you learn the Unstable Spell metamagic. It doesn't count against your total number of metamagics known, and it costs you 1 Sorcery Point to use.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Reaction">
			<description>For the next metamagic you apply on a spell after using Bend Luck or after a Wild Magic surge, its sorcery point cost is reduced by 1 (minimum 0). You can only reduce the sorcery point cost this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus per long rest. In addition, at 6th level you learn the Unstable Spell metamagic. It doesn't count against your total number of metamagics known, and it costs you 1 Sorcery Point to use.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Controlled Chaos" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_CONTROLLED_CHAOS">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>14th-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>At 14th level, you gain a modicum of control over the surges of your wild magic. Whenever you roll on the Wild Magic Surge table, you can roll twice and use either number. You also gain the ability to force a Wild Magic Surge at a moment of your choosing. As an action, you may momentarily embrace chaos. You do not need to roll a d10; simply roll for the Wild Magic Surge Table. Once you cause a surge with this feature, you can't do so again until the next day, unless you choose to spend 7 Sorcery Points to use it again. Using this action does not break concentration for spells.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Whenever you roll on the Wild Magic Surge table, you can roll twice and use either number. You also gain the ability to force a Wild Magic Surge at a moment of your choosing. As an action, you may momentarily embrace chaos. You do not need to roll a d10; simply roll for the Wild Magic Surge Table. Once you cause a surge with this feature, you can't do so again until the next day. Using this action does not break concentration for spells. You can spend 7 sorcery points to use this feature again.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Spell Bombardment" type="Archetype Feature" source="Marco's Homebrew" id="ID_AWMS_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPELL_BOMBARDMENT">
		<supports>Wild Magic</supports>
		<description>
			<p><em>18th-level Wild Magic feature</em></p>
			<p>Beginning at 18th level, the harmful energy of your spells intensifies. When you roll damage for a spell and roll the highest number possible on any of the dice, choose one of those dice, roll it again and add that roll to the damage. You can use the feature only once per turn. Additionally, whenever you have a Wild Magic Surge, you can use your reaction to have any effects from the Wild Magic Surge Table that would have otherwise targeted you and instead direct it to a creature you can see within 60 feet. If the effect can prevent the target from taking actions, the targeted creature will have to make a wisdom saving throw against your spell DC. If they succeed, no effect happens.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When you roll damage for a spell and roll the highest number possible on any of the dice, choose one of those dice, roll it again and add that roll to the damage. You can use the feature only once per turn. Additionally, whenever you have a Wild Magic Surge, you can use your reaction to have any effects from the Wild Magic Surge Table that would have otherwise targeted you and instead direct it to a creature you can see within 60 feet. If the effect can prevent the target from taking actions, the targeted creature will have to make a wisdom saving throw against your spell DC. If they succeed, no effect happens.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CHAOS_BOLT">
		<supports>Chaos Bolt</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_FAERIE_FIRE">
		<supports>Faerie Fire</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MISTY_STEP">
		<supports>Misty Step</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_WOTC_FTOD_SPELL_NATHAIRS_MISCHIEF">
		<supports>Nathair's Mischief</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BLINK">
		<supports>Blink</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_HYPNOTIC_PATTERN">
		<supports>Hypnotic Pattern</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CONFUSION">
		<supports>Confusion</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_POLYMORPH">
		<supports>Polymorph</supports>
	</append>	
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_CREATION">
		<supports>Creation</supports>
	</append>
	<append id="ID_PHB_SPELL_BIGBYS_HAND">
		<supports>Bigby's Hand</supports>
	</append>
</elements>
